Guide to the Berman Family papers, 1925-1989 MS 750
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Berman Family papers
1925-1989
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Berman family; Abramson, Ida Sue; Berman, Morton
MS 750
1.50 Linear Feet 2 boxes
The collection includes one box of correspondence; certificates of military service, public school attendance, marriage, and training; news clippings and part of a newsletter; a conference program; genealogy materials; and numerous photographs of family, friends, and events which document the history and activities of members of the Berman family from 1925 to 1989.
Biographical / Historical
Louis Berman and Ethel "Ettie" Kornweiser were born January 16, 1884, and July 30, 1889, respectively, in Slonim, Grodno Region, Poland in what is today Belarus. The two immigrated to the United States through New York in July 1905, eventually settling in Houston where Louis was a brick layer by trade. They were married June 9, 1907, and had nine children: Philip, David, Fanny, Rosalie, Joseph, Dorothy, Morris, Abraham, and Hymie, all born in Houston, with the exception of Philip who was born in Pennsylvania. Louis was a bricklayer by trade. Louis died May 27, 1951, and Ettie on March 22, 1977. Both are interred at Adath Israel Cemetery in Houston.
Louis and Ettie's son, David "Dave" Berman, was born October 15, 1909 in Houston. Anna Sohmers was born in Poland in 1915 and immigrated to the United States with her family in 1923. She and Dave were married in March of 1932 and had three children: Morton, Bernard, and Ida Sue. The family were members of Congregation Beth Yeshurun in Houston. When he was young, Dave was a member of the B.I.C. Club, which is said to stand for the Hebrew words meaning "Mighty Men of Israel." The club was organized in 1932 by young Jewish men interested in maintaining Jewish social contacts and enjoying athletic activities. Dave died October 8, 1969 and Anna on March 14, 2002 and both are interred at Brookside Memorial Park.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence; certificates of military service, public school attendance, marriage, and training; news clippings and part of a newsletter; a conference program; genealogy materials; and photographs of family, friends, and events document the history and activities of members of the Berman family from 1925 to 1989. Of particular interest are the numerous photographs of Dave Berman througout his life from childhood to middle age, including photos of his activities with the B.I.C. Club.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center and requires 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ida Sue Abramson and Morton Berman donated the papers in April 2018 and February 2018, respectively.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged in three series as follows:
Series I: Books; Series II: General; Series III: Oversize
Related Materials
The following collections contain materials for relatives of Fannie Berman and her descendants: MS 716, Pryzant Family Papers; MS 839, Miron / Berman Family Papers; MS 919, Chaskin / Hecht Family Papers
Index Terms
Subjects
Genealogy; Jews and Jewish life
Document Types
certificates; personal correspondence; books; clippings (information artifacts); newsletters; programs (documents); photographs
Subjects (Persons)
Abramson, Ida Sue; Berman, Morton
- Series I: Books, 1942-1954
  - Prayers of Israel, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Sabbath: the Day of Delight by Abraham K. Millgram with inscription to Morton Berman from Rabbi Max Geller on the occasion of Morton's 1946 Bar Mitzvah, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Beth Yeshurun Sunday School book and announcement belonging to Ida Sue Berman, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Centenary History - Congregation Beth Israel of Houston, Texas, 1954-1994 (Box 1)
- Series II: General
  - Houston Public Schools Certificate of Attainment to Dave Berman, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Group photographs (8), some from B.I.C. events, 1929-1940s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Family photographs (11), c. 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Military certificates, 1932; 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Marriage certificate for Dave Berman and Anna Sohmers, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Louis and Ethel "Ettie" Berman, c. 1940s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Genealogy materials, 1949-2011 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Group photograph, c. 1940s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dave Berman with bowling team, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - News clippings, 1952-1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Certificate, Harris County Sheriff's Office to Dave Berman, 1958-05-29 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Workmen's Circle Conference program, 1965-09-04-1965-09-07 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - B.I.C. reunion photos, 1984; 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - B.I.C. Club correspondence and reunion flyer, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Page from Seven Acres "Homefront Highlights", 1987-1990s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Postcard to Ann Berman from her daughter, Susie, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Fred Mosk with trophy, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sam Miron, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Hollywood Tailors interior with business card, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Exterior building photos (2), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Photograph of couple inscribed to Dave and Ann Berman from Sam and Spoosty (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Dave Berman's grammar school class, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Series III: Oversize
  - Copeland/Berman families, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Beth Yeshurun group photo, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 2)